Guide to the Jay F. Rosenberg Papers, 1956-2008 ASP.2008.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Manuscripts from Others, 1931-1982; IV.
  - Manuscripts by Wilfrid Sellars, 1947-1982; 1.
    - On the Introduction of Abstract Entities, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - On the Logic of Complex Particulars, Undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Ontology and the Philosophy of Mind in Russell, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - The Paradox of Analysis Resolved, Undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Partial Manuscript; pages 10-58, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Induction as Vindication; Philosophy of Science, July 1964 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Physical Realism; Philosophical and Phenomenological Research, Vol. XV, No. 1, pp. 13-32, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Pure Pragmatics and Epistemology, Undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Reply; 27, pp. 457-466, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Reply to Alan Donagan, Undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Reply to Aune, Undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Reply to Marras, Undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Reply to Quine, Undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - The Role of the Imagination in Kant's Theory of Experience, Undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Science and Ethics, Undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Science, Sense Impressions and Sensa: A Reply to Cornman, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - R.C. Richardson and G. Muilenburg: Sellars and Sense Impressions, Undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Sellars on Kant, Undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Sensa or Sensings: Reflections on the Ontology of Perception; Philosophical Studies, 41, pp. 83-111, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Some Problems About Belief, Undated (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Some Reflections on Thoughts and Things, Undated (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Some Reflections on Perceptual Consciousness, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Some Remarks on Kant's Theory of Experience, Undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - The Soul as Craftsman, Undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - The Structure of Knowledge: (3) Epistemic Principles, Undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - The Structure of Knowledge: Perception, Undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Substance and Form in Aristotle, Undated (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - ...this I or he or it (the thing) which thinks..., Undated (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Thought and Action, Undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Towards a Theory of Predication, Undated (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Toward a Theory of the Categories, Undated (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Untitled Manuscript, Undated (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - The Adverbial Theory of the Objects of Sensation, Undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - A Sectioning of Descartes' First Meditation, Undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Behaviorism, Language, and Meaning, Undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Belief and the Expression of Belief, Undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Berkeley and Descartes: Reflections on the Theory of Ideas, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Concepts as Involving Laws and Inconceivable Without Them, Undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Conditional Promises and Conditional Intentions (including a reply to Castaneda), 1980 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Conceptual Change, Undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Contemporary Analytic Philosophy, Undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - The Double-Knowledge Approach to the Mind-Body Problem, Undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Epistemology and the New Way of Words; Journal of Philosophy, Vol. XLIV, No. 24, 20 November, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Fatalism and Determinism, Undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Form and Content in Ethical Theory, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Foundations of Knowledge, Undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - General Discussion of Sellars' Paper, Undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Givenness and Explanatory Coherence, Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Grammar and Existence: A Preface to Ontology, Undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Hochberg on Mapping, Meaning, and Metaphysics; Midwest Studies in Philosophy, II: 214-224, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Inference and Meaning, Undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Is Scientific Realism Tenable? (A), Undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Is Scientific Realism Tenable? (B), Undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Kant's Transcendental Idealism; Kant's Analytic pp. 166-181, Undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Language as Thought and as Communication, Undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Literatur, Undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Meaning as Functional Classification, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - On Accepting First Principles, Undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - On the Radical Incompleteness of the Manifest Image, Undated (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - On Reasoning about Values, Undated (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - The Logical Way of Doing Things, Undated (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Manuscripts from Others, 1931, 1980; 2.
    - Bechtel, William: Levels of Description and Explanation in Cognitive Science, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Bonjour, Laurence and Ernest Sosa: Red Triangles and Speckled Hens; IJPS, 12 (4), 465-79, Undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Bradley, Francis Herbert: Relation and Quality Ch. III; Appearance and Reality: A Metaphysical Essay, Undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Cornman, James W.: Sellars, Scientific Realism, and Sensa (B), Undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Fogelin, Robert J.: Contextualism and Externalism: Trading in One Form of Skepticism for Another, Undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Hanna, Patricia: The World, the Elephant and the Tortoise, Undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Lavin, Michael: The Thinking Self, Undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Rescher: Comments on Rescher's Scientific Truth and the Arbitrament of Praxis; Western Pa, (B), 1980 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Rorty, Richard: Brandom's Making it Explicit: A First Encounter (B), Undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Seibt, Johanna: Review of Properties as Processes... (B), Undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Van Fraassen, Bas: Is Scientific Realism Tenable? (B), Undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Wittgenstein, L.: Complex and Fact (B), 1931 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Wittgenstein, L.: Complex and Fact; Rosenberg Translation, Undated (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Views on Schlesinger; Multiple Authors, Undated (Box 15, Folder 14)
- Teaching Materials, 1950-2006; V.
  Rosenberg taught many different courses during his long career. This section contains manuscripts of his undergraduate and graduate courses at the University of North Carolina. They are arranged by course number, and within series of multiple offerings of the same course, chronologically by year.
  - Philosophy 21, 1950-1961 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Junior Qualifying Exam, April 1962 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - PHIL 006F Sec 002; Seminar of Death, Fall 2000 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Death as a Problem for Philosophy; Freshman Seminar; PHIL 006F Sec 002, Fall 2000 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - PHIL 20/ PHIL 24H, Spring 1992 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - PHIL 20/PHIL 24, Spring 1999 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - PHIL 20/20E, Fall 2001 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - PHIL 20/20E, (2), Fall 2001 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - PHIL 24 Sec 001; Historical Info: General Support, Spring 1991 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - PHIL 24 Introduction to Philosophy: Classical Historical Texts, Fall 1992 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - PHIL 24 Introduction to Philosophy: Classical Historical Texts, (2), Fall 1992 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - PHIL 24H SEC. 001 An Introduction to Philosophy: Great Works, Fall (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - PHIL 73, Spring 2002 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - PHIL 73, Spring 2004 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - PHIL 96 Colloquium for Undergraduate Majors, Spring 1998 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - PHIL 111 Propositional Calculi, Spring 1967 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - PHIL 114 Beginnings of Analytic Philosophy; Frege, Russell, and Moore, 1989, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - PHIL 114 Beginnings of Analytic Philosophy, Undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - PHIL 114 Beginnings of Analytic Philosophy (2), Undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - PHIL 155 Kant, 1997 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - PHIL 203 Ontological Alternatives, Spring 1988 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - PHIL 204 Epistemology, Posman, 1997 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - PHIL 206 The Philosophy of Wilfrid Sellars, Fall 1986 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - PHIL 206 Philosophy of the Mind, Fall 1990 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - PHIL 206 The Philosophy of Wilfrid Sellars, Spring 1994 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - PHIL 206 Contemporary Analytic Philosophy: Wilfrid Sellars, Spring 1994 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - PHIL 206, Philosophical Investigations, Fall 2001 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - PHIL 206, Full notes on the Tractatus-On Representation, Undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - PHIL 220 Kant, Spring 2006 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - PHIL 235 Epistemology, Spring 2004 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - PHIL 300 Protoseminar, Spring 2001 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - PHIL 300 Protoseminar, Spring 2002 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Notes on the Tractarian Theory, Fall 1971 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - On Reasoning About Values, September 27, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Tractatus Logice--Philosophicus, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Protoseminar, Spring 2001 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - The Philosophy of Wilfrid Sellars, Spring 2005 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Berkeley: Three Dialogues, Undated (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Brandom: Making It Explicit, Undated (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Sellars, Undated (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Descartes: Meditations, Undated (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Epistemology, Undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Epistemology (2), Undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Hume: Treatise of Human Nature, Undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Modern PHIL Area Exam, Undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - The Philosophy of Wilfrid Sellars-Notes and Reading Lists, Undated (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Plato: Euthyphro, Undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Plato: Meno, Undated (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Power Point Presentation, Undated (Box 22, Folder 8)
- Library Preprints and Reprints, 1948-2006; VI.
  The reprints, preprints and other versions of published professional essays are annotated by Rosenberg and kept. Unannotated reprints were not retained.
  - Reprints (A), 1966-1987; 1.; 24 folders (Box 23)
  - Reprints (B), 1988-2004; 2.; 25 folders (Box 24)
  - Annotations (A), 1948-1975; 3.; 13 folders (Box 25)
  - Annotations (B), 1976-2006; 4.; 14 folders (Box 26)
- Rosenberg Miscellaneous Personal Papers, 1963-2008; VII.
  The Rosenberg Archive also contains a small collection of personal materials including non-professional manuscripts Rosenberg created while studying philosophy as an undergraduate student at Reed College. Other materials include Rosenberg's obituary, a DVD containing a memorial presentation of photographs of Rosenberg, and his curriculum vitae.
  - Student Materials, 1964; 1.
    - I Exist and Pragmatic Self-Verification, 1964 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - A Note on Tensed Discourse and the Eliminability of the Tenses, 1964 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 2.
    - DVD-Jay's Memorial Video (9:01), Undated (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Non-professional Manuscripts, 2002; 3.
    - The Impoverished Students' Book of Cookery, Drinkery, & Housekeepery, 2002 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Obituaries and Curriculum Vitae, 2008; 4.
    - Obituary, 2008 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Proceedings and Addresses of the American Philosophical Association Vol. 2, Issue 2, November; Rosenberg's Obituary p. 164, 2008 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Rosenberg's Curriculum Vitae, 1963-2007 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Conference, 2008; 5.
    - Self, Language, and World: Themes in Philosophy of Jay F. Rosenberg, September 2008 (Box 27, Folder 8)
- Wilfrid Sellars' Miscellaneous Personal Papers and Photographs, 1960-1990; VIII.
  Rosenberg was a student of Sellars while working on his Ph.D. at the University of Pittsburgh. They kept up contact throughout the remainder of Sellars' career. Hence this collection contains letters, other documents, and especially photographs that will be of interest to historians and philosophers studying Sellars' philosophy.
  - Wilfrid Sellars' Personal Papers, 1960-1990; 1.
    - Sellars' Estate Correspondence, 1960,1965-66,1968 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Memorandum of Agreement, R.W. Sellars and Arthur Glasgow, 1964 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - "The Irvine Lexicon" ed. by D.C. Dennett, Undated (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Personal Miscellaneous, 1937,1954-55,1958,1961 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Sellars' Bibliography compiled by Andrew Chrucky, Undated (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Andrew Chrucky "Critique of Wilfrid Sellars' 'Materialism'", 1990 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Sellars' Photographs, 1970-1987; 2.
    The photographs found here are an interesting and useful addition to photographs found in the Sellars Archive. They include multiple photographs of Sellars in early, middle, and later life as well photographs of Sellars and other major philosophers at conferences and conventions.
    - Photographs of Wilfrid Sellars with Colleagues, 1973-1974 and undated. (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of Wilfrid with Colleagues (2), Undated (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Photographs of Wilfrid in youth, Undated (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Photographs of Wilfrid in middle life (1), Undated (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Photographs of Wilfrid in middle life (2), Undated (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Photographs of Wilfrid with Family, 1970, Undated (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous photographs of flowers, koi carp, etc., 1980-81, 1987, Undated (Box 28, Folder 14)